A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 6, Accession 6 FA1188
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 6, Accession 6
1966-2009
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations
FA1188
19.09 Cubic Feet 49 document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist. When requesting audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China. The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach. Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
Scope and Contents
RG 6 of the National Committee on United States – China Relations records (1966-2009) particularly documents the National Committee's programs and activities during its formative years from the late 1960s through the 1970s. Materials include Board, Committee, and Members records, which document the NCUSCR's early program discussions and overall organizational history; records of public education and outreach programs in the early 1970s; and records documenting the National Committee's role in brokering information and facilitating exchanges in the 1970s-1980s. Other significant materials include records in the Development series of the National Committee's contract work for the U. S. Information Agency, the Department of State, and other government departments in the late 1980s – 2000s, and of grant support it received from various private foundations.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received minimal physical rearrangement. RG 6 of the NCUSCR records is arranged into seven series: 1 – Events; 2 – Exchanges - General; 3 – Exchanges to China; 8 – Programs, Projects, and Proposals; 10 – Development; 11 – Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records; and 15 – Clippings and Reference.
- Events, 1968-1975, 2008; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Events series in RG 6 documents a series of public outreach programs the National Committee undertook in the early 1970s as a way of engaging members, attracting financial support, and fostering knowledge and awareness of China. The stand-alone events (usually luncheons, dinners, or one-day meetings) included Business Programs, Speaker Tours, and Regional Symposia on issues of U. S. – China relations. The Regional Symposia were frequently organized in cooperation with local World Affairs Councils.
  - Wen Jiabao Luncheon, 2008 September 23 (Box 15, Folder 151)
    Waldorf-Astoria.
  - Business Programs: China Trade Briefing, 1970 April 20 (Box 46, Folder 403)
  - Business Programs: John A. Morgan Dinner (New York), 1970 October 23 (Box 46, Folder 404)
  - Business Programs: John Lindbeck Luncheon (New York ) (Cancelled), 1970 November 16 (Box 46, Folder 405)
  - Business Programs: Pat Clever Luncheons (New York and San Francisco), 1970 November 17-19 (Box 46, Folder 406)
  - Los Angeles Junior Chamber of Commerce Seminar on China, 1970 November 18 (Box 46, Folder 407)
  - Business Programs: Ole Algard Dinner (New York), 1970 December 15 (Box 46, Folder 408)
  - Michigan Business Seminar, 1971 September 22-23 (Box 46, Folder 409)
    Trade Prospects in the PRC
  - Business Programs: Hawaii Program, 1971 September 30-October 1 (Box 46, Folder 410)
    Doing Business in the PRC
  - Business Programs: Wallace Chavkin Luncheon (New York), 1972 May 25 (Box 46, Folder 411)
  - Center for International Business Conference (Los Angeles), 1972 June 12-13 (Box 46, Folder 412)
    China: New Perspectives for Trade and Investment with the PRC and the Republic of China (Taiwan).
  - John Diebold and Alexander Eckstein Luncheon (New York), 1973 February 1 (Box 46, Folder 413)
  - Trade Conference - Seattle, 1973 April 30-May 1 (Box 46, Folder 414)
    Seattle Symposium: China, Japan and the Pacific Northwest: New Opportunities for Trade, Transport and Investment.
  - Trade Conference - Akron, 1973 June 6 (Box 46, Folder 415)
    The People's Republic of China and Japan: The Changing International Business Kaleidoscope in the Far East.
  - Business Luncheon (New York), 1973 November 27 (Box 46, Folder 416)
    First in a series of luncheon meetings for businessmen concerned with U. S. - China Trade.
  - Business Luncheon (New York), 1974 February 4 (Box 46, Folder 417)
    Second in a series of luncheon meetings for businessmen concerned with U. S. - China Trade. Topic: Legal Aspects of Trading with China.
  - Speakers - Stanley Karnow, 1968 April (Box 47, Folder 418)
    File includes 5 x 7 black and white portrait of Stanley Karnow, Hong Kong Bureau Chief, Washington Post.
  - Speakers - William Brugger, 1970-1971 (Box 47, Folder 419)
  - Speakers - Roland Berger, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 420)
  - Speakers - John S. Service, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 421)
  - Speakers - Tadao Ishikawa, 1974 May (Box 47, Folder 422)
  - Regional Symposia: General, 1970-1971 (Box 47, Folder 423)
    Includes proposals for symposia in Los Angeles, Houston, and Atlanta.
  - Regional Symposia: Programs, 1971-1973 (Box 47, Folder 424)
  - Symposia: Possible Partner Organizations, 1969-1973 (Box 47, Folder 425)
    Reference file.
  - St. Louis Regional Symposium, 1971 April 15 (Box 47, Folder 426)
    U. S. and China in the 1970s: Reconciliation or Confrontation.
  - Boston Regional Symposium, 1971 May 12 (Box 47, Folder 427)
    America's China Policy: The Coming Crisis
  - San Francisco Regional Symposium, 1971 May 20 (Box 47, Folder 428)
    Prospects and Problems for U. S. Trade with the People's Republic of China.
  - Pittsburgh Regional Symposium, 1971 October 19-20 (Box 47, Folder 429)
    China, the United States, and the United Nations.
  - Pittsburgh Regional Symposium, 1971 October 19-20 (Box 48, Folder 430)
  - Minneapolis Regional Symposium, 1971 November 4 (Box 48, Folder 431)
    Conference on the U. S. and China in Asia.
  - American Society for Public Administration Conference (Los Angeles), 1972-1973 (Box 48, Folder 432)
    Comparative Administration Group of the ASPA. Conference held April 1973.
  - China Flying Seminar (Great Neck Public Schools), 1973 May (Box 48, Folder 433)
  - Regional Members Meetings (General), 1973-1974 (Box 48, Folder 434)
  - Indianapolis Consultation on China, 1973 May 15 (Box 48, Folder 435)
    Indianapolis World Affairs Council.
  - Los Angeles Members Meeting, 1973 October 19 (Box 48, Folder 436)
  - Regional Meetings (San Francisco World Affairs Council), 1973 November 14-16 (Box 48, Folder 437)
    Charles Yost's visit also included meeting at Stanford and Members meeting.
  - Pittsburgh Symposium, 1973 November 28-29 (Box 48, Folder 438-439)
    Conference, Relating to China: A new look at U. S. - China detente and trade prospects. Cosponsored with the World Affairs Council and the University of Pittsburgh, in cooperation with the National Council for U. S. - China Trade.
  - Atlanta Meetings, 1973 December 12 (Box 48, Folder 440)
    Charles Yost meetings, Southern Council on International and Public Affairs.
  - Chicago Council on Foreign Relations Seminars, 1974 January-February (Box 48, Folder 441)
    Charles Yost and others.
  - Regional Meetings (Southern California World Affairs Councils), 1974 May (Box 48, Folder 442)
    Charles Yost meetings in San Diego, Los Angeles, Orange County, and Palm Springs. File includes a 4 x 6 black and white portrait photo of Yost.
  - Members Dinner, Symposium, and Meeting (Washington, DC), 1974 June 3-4 (Box 49, Folder 443)
    Joint dinner with the National Council for U. S. - China Trade and the Committee on Scholarly Communication with China, at which Henry Kissinger was the expected speaker. Planning correspondence.
  - Regional Meetings (Toledo and Philadelphia World Affairs Councils), 1974 September -1975 April (Box 49, Folder 444)
    Charles Yost talks.
  - Minneapolis Conference, 1974 October 31 (Box 49, Folder 445)
    China and the World Community
  - Boston Bib and Chowder Society (World Affairs Council of Boston), 1974 November 11-12 (Box 49, Folder 446)
    Conference on China and the U. S.: Factors Shaping Detente, preceded by dinner with Ambassador Philip C. Habib.
  - Ambassador George H. Bush Luncheon (Cancelled), 1975 January 30 (Box 49, Folder 447)
    Cosponsored with the Asia Society.
- Exchanges - General, 1972-1983; 2
  The general Exchanges series in RG 6 reflects awakening interest among Americans in the 1970s in visiting China. The series contains inquiries and proposals to the National Committee from various unaffiliated groups or individuals who were interested in arranging exchange trips to China, particularly in the performing arts, business, medicine, and sports.
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Dance, 1973-1981 (Box 38, Folder 327-329)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Drama, 1973-1983 (Box 38, Folder 330-331)
    Folder 330 includes black and white photo.
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Opera, 1973-1980 (Box 38, Folder 332)
    Includes black and white photos.
  - Metropolitan Opera, 1974-1977 (Box 38, Folder 333)
    Interest in co-sponsoring Chinese Opera tour of U.S., Metropolitan Opera Japan Tour, 1975. The Metropolitan Opera helped sponsor the U. S. visit of the Chinese Performing Arts Company in July-August 1978. Folder includes black and white photos from the Japan visit.
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Orchestras and Music Ensembles, 1972-1979 (Box 39, Folder 334-336)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Management, Business, and Trade, 1973-1981 (Box 39, Folder 337-338)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Medical Exchanges (General), 1973-1979 (Box 39, Folder 339-340)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Medical Exchanges (Dental), 1973-1980 (Box 39, Folder 341)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Medical Exchanges (Mental Health, Psychology, Psychiatry), 1972-1980 (Box 40, Folder 342)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Medical Students, 1973-1980 (Box 40, Folder 343)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Publishing, 1973-1977 (Box 40, Folder 344)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Religious Groups, 1974-1975 (Box 40, Folder 345)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Urban Planning, 1972-1977 (Box 40, Folder 346)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges -Sports, 1972-1981 (Box 40, Folder 347-350)
    Folder 349 includes some black and white photos.
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - Mount Everest Expedition, 1974-1980 (Box 41, Folder 351)
  - Outside Proposals for Exchanges - People-to-People Sports Committee, 1973-1975 (Box 41, Folder 352)
  - Sports Exchanges - General Information, 1973-1978 (Box 41, Folder 353)
- Exchanges to China, 1978-2004; 3
  The Exchanges to China series in RG 6 documents the National Committee's Members Trips from 1978-1986. It also includes briefing books and applications for the Fulbright-Hays Summer Seminars to China, 2002-2004.
  - Members Delegations (General), 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    Inquiries about joining trips.
  - Members Delegations (General), 1978-1981 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    Mainly correspondence with Luxingshe concerning dates, travel arrangements, and finances.
  - Members Delegation (1978, No. 1), 1978 October 3-23 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Members Delegation (1978, No. 2), 1978 December 1-17 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Members Delegation (1979, No. 1), 1979 May 10-28 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Members Delegation (1979, No. 2), 1979 October 20-November 7 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Members Delegation (1979, No. 3), 1979 November 5-24 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Members Delegation (1980, No. 1), 1980 May 7-28 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Members Delegation (1980, No. 1) (Report), 1980 May 7-28 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Members Delegation (1980, No. 2), 1980 September 10-29 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Members Delegation (1980, No. 3), 1980 October 9-28 (Box 9, Folder 95)
    Original folder labeled, MD [Members Delegation] No. 3 IBM.
  - Members Delegation (1980, No. 4), 1980 October 18-November 10 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Art Study Delegation, 1980 October 6-November 6 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    Self-financed group
  - Members Delegations (1981, Nos. 1-3) (Box 9, Folder 98)
    Delegation No. 1, 1981 May 1-17, No. 2, 1981 September 5-25, No. 3 (Cancelled), scheduled for 1981 September 11-30.
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 4), 1981 October 24-November 12 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Lawyers Delegation (Cancelled), 1981 October 24-November 12 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Members Trips, 1982-1984 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Members Trip, 1986 November 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Briefing Book for Visitors to China, circa 1997 June (Box 14, Folder 137-138)
    Unidentified or general briefing book, revised June 1997. Includes travel information, background material, and selected articles.
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Briefing Book, 2002 (Box 14, Folder 139-140)
    Fulbright Summer Seminars to China.
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Briefing Book, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 141)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Applications, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 142-144)
    Fulbright -Hays Seminars Abroad Program.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Applications, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 145)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Applications, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 145A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - confidential material.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Applications, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 146-149)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Applications, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 149A)
- Programs, Projects, and Proposals, 2005; 8
  - Volunteerism Training and Development, 2005, undated (Box 15, Folder 150)
    Reference file. Includes: Development Phases in the Establishment of a Volunteer Center (handbook), Training on "NGO basics" for Chinese grass root NGOs (syllabus, China Association for NGO Cooperation, CANGO), Volunteerism conference, Hong Kong, 2005.
- Development, 1968-2009; 10
  The Development series in RG 6 contains records of the NCUSCR's funding from the U. S. government and private foundations. Files include proposals, grant applications, narrative and financial reports, and grant-related correspondence. Grants from the U. S. Information Agency (1985-2002), the U. S. Department of State (1998-2006), the Department of Education (1987-2007), and the Department of Labor (2002-2007), funded the National Committee's administration of the Fulbright seminars and educational exchange programs, as well as some cooperative projects. The USIA's grants to the National Committee became the subject of congressional investigation in the late 1990s; when the USIA was abolished in 1999, the State Department assumed responsibility for its exchange programs. This series also documents grants from private foundations, including the Ford Foundation (1988-2009), the Luce Foundation (1979-1999), the MacArthur Foundation (1987-2007), and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1979-1997), among others. Additional records relating to foundation funding are found in RG 5 (FA1187).
  - Final Report to the Ford Foundation on Grants 875-0392, 860-1045, and 860-0791, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 152)
    Grant 08600791 (South Asian Studies Delegation to the U. S., Latin American Studies Delegation to the U. S., and Mideast Studies Delegation to the U. S.), Grant 08601045 (Young Economists' Delegation to the U. S., also described as Economic Reform Research Delegation), Grant 08750392 (Binational Delegation to the U. S. - U. S. - China Dialogue, 1987).
  - Proposal and Final Reports to the Ford Foundation for Fiscal Years 1993 and 1994, 1992 -1995 (Box 16, Folder 153)
    Proposal, 1992, and reports for fiscal years 1993 and 1994. Mainly concerning funding for Scholar Orientation Program and U. S. - China Dialogues.
  - Report to the Ford Foundation for Fiscal Year 1995, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 154)
  - Narrative and Financial Reports to the Ford Foundation for Fiscal Years 1996-2001 (Box 16, Folder 155-158)
  - Narrative and Financial Reports to the Ford Foundation for Fiscal Year 2002, 2003-2004 (Box 17, Folder 159)
  - Final Report to the Ford Foundation on Grant 09900757, Fiscal Year 2003, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 160)
  - Ford Foundation: Correspondence (General), 1989-1992 (Box 17, Folder 161)
  - Ford Foundation: Scholar Orientation Program, 1989-1998 (Box 17, Folder 162-163)
  - Ford Foundation: Facilitative Assistance, 1992-1997 (Box 17, Folder 164)
  - Ford Foundation: Middle East Studies Delegation to China, 1989-1991 (Box 17, Folder 165)
  - Ford Foundation: State Council Development Research Center Delegation, 1991-1993 (Box 17, Folder 166)
  - Ford Foundation: State Council Center for International Studies Delegation, 1993-1995 (Box 17, Folder 167)
  - Ford Foundation: Judicial Workshops in China Proposal, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 168)
  - Ford Foundation: Judicial Reform, Delegations, and Training, 1996-2003 (Box 18, Folder 169-172)
    Workshops and judges' delegations from China. Includes grants 09651279, 10250879, 09701377, and 09650600. File additionally sorted into Fax Correspondence, E-Mail Correspondence, Budget and Financial Information.
  - Ford Foundation: Strengthening the Work of Chinese Legal Aid Centers, 2004-2005 (Box 18, Folder 173)
    Grant 10450947, also funds from grants 09651279 and 10250879. Folder labeled "Legal Aid Activists."
  - Ford Foundation: Survey of Programs on International Relations, 2002-2009 (Box 18, Folder 174)
    Survey of Programs on United States-China Relations and Security Issues. The National Committee conducted the survey for the Ford Foundation. File mainly concerns budget and grant administration.
  - Ford Foundation: Cross-Strait Conference, 2003-2004 (Box 18, Folder 175)
    New Risks and Opportunities in the Taiwan Strait: Defining America's Role, 2003 August 8-10, Pocantico Conference Center.
  - Ford Foundation: Health Emergency Conference (FY2003), 2003-2004 (Box 18, Folder 176)
    Grant 10351674 for videoconference to China on public health emergency management in the United States.
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1986 (IA-22445-19G), 1985-1989 (Box 18, Folder 177)
    Grant award, budget, and reporting.
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-PSMA-G8193418, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 178)
    Report on the Visit of the China Central Television Management Delegation to the U. S., 1988 September 7-27.
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1989 (IA-PSMA-G9193518), 1988-1991 (Box 19, Folder 179-181)
    Correspondence and budgeting. Includes proposal, agreement and amendments, and financial reports.
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency on Grant IA-PSMA-G9193518, 1988 December -1991 May (Box 19, Folder 182)
    Delegation trip reports and itineraries.
  - United States Information Agency: Grant IA-PSMA-G9193780 (Cantonese-Speaking Journalists Delegation), 1989-1990 (Box 19, Folder 183)
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1990 (IA-PSMA-G0190070), 1989-1992 (Box 19, Folder 184-185)
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency on Grant IA-PSMA-G0190070, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 186)
  - United States Information Agency: Fulbright Grant for FY 1990 (IA-AEMA-G0190369), 1988, 1990-1992 (Box 20, Folder 187)
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-AEMA-G0190369, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 188)
  - Proposal to the United States Information Agency for FY 1991 (Grant IA-PSMA-G1190093), 1990 October (Box 20, Folder 189)
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1991 (IA-PSMA-G1190093), 1990-1993 (Box 20, Folder 190)
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency on Grant IA-PSMA-G1190093, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 191)
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1992 (IA-PSCS-G2190065), 1991-1993 (Box 21, Folder 192)
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-PSCS-G219065, 1993 (Box 21, Folder 193)
  - Proposal to the United States Information Agency for FY 1992 (Fulbright Program), 1991 September (Box 21, Folder 194)
    A chart of the NCUSCR's Education Program (1966-1977) and Exchange Program (1977-1986) has been separated to box 50.
  - Proposals to the United States Information Agency for FY 1992 (RFP Grants) (Box 21, Folder 195)
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1993 (IA-PSPS-G3190078), 1992-1995 (Box 21, Folder 196-197)
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-PSPS-G3190078, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 198)
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-PSPS-G3190078, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 199)
  - Proposal to the United States Information Agency for FY 1994, 1993 September (Box 22, Folder 200-202)
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1994 (IA-PSPS-G4190090), 1993-1996 (Box 22, Folder 203)
  - Report to the United States Information Agency on FY 1994 Grant IA-PSPS-G4190090, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 204-205)
  - United States Information Agency: Grant for FY 1995 (IA-PSPS-G5190089), 1994-1997 (Box 23, Folder 206-207)
    Includes Proposal, September 1994.
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-PSPS-G5190089, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 208-209)
  - Proposals to the United States Information Agency (Projects on American Federalism and Chinese Local Elected Officials), 1995 (Box 23, Folder 210-211)